Ludwik and Juliana Trzcinski Collection CPAA 91.04
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Ludwik and Juliana Trzcinski Collection
1890-1980
CPAA 91.04
Connecticut Polish American Archives
2.0 Linear feet
The Ludwik and Juliana Trzcinski collection consists of materials reflecting their lives in New Britain, Connecticut. The Trzcinski's were first generation of Polish immigrants. They actively participated in Sacred Heart parish and school. Family members belonged to various religious societies and veterans organizations. Items in collection range in dates from the 1890’s all the way to the 1980’s. There are many family and professional photographs of family gatherings, weddings, first communions, and other church related events.
Trzcinski, Juliana
Trzcinski, Ludwik
Scope and Contents note
Extensive collection of photographs, mostly family, school and social activities from about 1890 until the 1980's; religious and family memorabilia.
Biographical/Historical note
Ludwik (d. 1954) and Juliana (Kalitan) Trzcinski were residents of New Britain, Connecticut. Ludwik died on November 27, 1954. Ludwik and Juliana lived in New Britian, Connecticut. Several religious items and Sacred Heart School memorabilia, especially Genovieve’s (daughter), are in the collection as well. Real estate documents relating to Mr. Trzcinski’s death are included in addition to general material concerning Polish heritage in Connecticut (calendars, newspaper articles, events).
Catholics -- Polish; Photographs; Polish Americans -- Connecticut; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- New Britain; Polish Americans -- Religious life; Sacred Heart School (New Britain, Conn.) -- History
- Ludwik and Juliana Trzcinski-documents re: estate, lease deed, funeral services, probate court. Inheritance document of property to Genevieve Trzcinski of Piqua, Kansas., 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Political advertisement for Probate Judge Henry J. Gwiazda., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- French speech for graduation in 1936 from Sacred Heart School, written by Father Alphonse Fiedorczyk, given by Jean Trzcinski. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Sacred Heart School photo-class of 1936. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Sacred Heart School certificate "swiadectwo szkolne", 1933 for John Trzcinski (Box 1, Folder 5)
- “Industrial development of New Britain CT” by John T. Trzcinski., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Maryann Cecilia Trzcinski-diploma of St. Joseph School, Norwich., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Family photographs: weddings, funerals, professional family photos, most captions on back in Polish. A note written in Polish., 1937-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Family photographs: several photos of Alexander Ruszczyk, wedding photos. Probably date to earlier than 1914., 1914-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lenten play at Sacred Heart school, 1940 photograph page. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Gen. Joseph Haller's visit to Sacred Heart church, New Britain, April 1940 (photos). (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Piesn na czas wojny WWII. Farewell song for WW II, Sacred Heart School., 1936; Box 1 Folder 12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Priests and Nuns (photos). 1940’s., 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Stations of the Cross, published by Przewodnik Katolicki, New Britian., 1924, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Sacred Heart church - Julianna's Trzcinski donation notebook, 1909-1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Trzcinski family - mounted photographs, 1910-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Society of St. Rose of Lima - group photo, 1930's (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Life and achievements of s.p. Archbishop Jan Cieplak, by Rev. F. Sznarbachowski, after 1926 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Stadttheater Luzern (Switzerland) program, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 18, Folder 19)
- "Tamburitzans" Dance group from Duguesne University brochures, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 19, Folder 20)
- Our Sunday Visitor - articles related to Polish immigrants, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20, Folder 21)
- 3 photo albums - family photos: weddings, first communions, graduations family gatherings., 1935-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Prayer book from 1929 given for the occasion of the 1st Communion to Genevieve (Genowefa) Trzcinska (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Collection of various calendars printed in Poland and Italy (Box 3, Folder 3, Box 2)
- Holy Cards, 1924-1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Family memorabilia: baptismal ribbon of Louis, Ed, Jean and John; Jean's pins; comb from 1920, wedding head crown - Oct. 14, 1913; scapulars and ribbons (Box 4)